Guide to the Robert Bartlett Haas Collection on Gertrude Stein and the Conference Press
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robert Bartlett Haas collection on Gertrude Stein and the Conference Press
1936-1985
YCAL MSS 833
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.47
(6 boxes)
The Robert Bartlett Haas Collection on Gertrude Stein and the Conference Press contains correspondence, drafts of writings, notes, photographs, printed material and papers relating to Getrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas, and the production and distribution of Conference Press publications, including Stein's What Are Masterpieces?
Haas, Robert Bartlett
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Robert Bartlett Haas, 1962-1995.
Custodial History
The 1962 acquisition was given to Robert Bartlett Haas by Hal Levy.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Box 3, 23 autograph letters signed and 2 autograph postcards signed from Alice B. Toklas to Robert Bartlett Haas, with original envelopes, 1946-1955, is also available on microfilm.
Robert Bartlett Haas (1916-2010)
Robert Bartlett Haas, American scholar and educator. Haas was born January 20, 1916, in Santa Cruz, California. He graduated with a bachelor's degree in English from the University of California, Berkeley in 1938, a master's in English from the University of Chicago and a doctorate in education from Stanford. He joined the University of California Los Angeles faculty in 1949 and was the founding director of the school's arts and humanities extension division. Haas remained at UCLA until his retirement in the late 1970s. He spent most of his retirement years in Nuertingen, Germany and died there after a brief illness, on April 20, 2010.
Haas's scholarship primarily focused on Gertrude Stein and he wrote several books on her, including A Catalogue of the Published and Unpublished Writings of Gertrude Stein (Yale University Library, 1941), Reflection on the Atomic Bomb: The Previously Uncollected Writings of Gertrude Stein, Volume I (Black Sparrow Press, 1973), and How Writing Is Written: Volume II of the Previously Uncollected Writings of Gertrude Stein (Black Sparrow Press, 1975). He also edited A Primer for the Gradual Understanding of Gertrude Stein (Black Sparrow Press, 1971).
The Conference Press was the creation of three UCLA students, Hal Levy, Gilbert A. Harrison, and William Bayard Okie. Harrison developed a friendship with Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas, which led to the publication of Stein's work What Are Masterpieces? by the Conference Press in 1940. During Bartlett's tenure at UCLA, he was involved in the publication and distribution process of the press and wrote the introduction to What Are Masterpieces?
Scope and Contents
The Robert Bartlett Haas Collection on Gertrude Stein and the Conference Press contains correspondence, drafts of writings, notes, photographs, printed material and papers relating to Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas, and production and distribution of Conference Press publications, including Stein's What Are Masterpieces?
Arrangement
Organized into five groupings: I. March 1962 Acquisition. II. December 1972 Acquisition. III. January 1986 Acquisition. IV. 1989 Acquisitions. V. May 1995 Acquisition.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Authors and publishers -- United States; Editors -- United States; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Photographic prints -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Editors -- United States -- 20th Century; Haas, Robert Bartlett; Harrison, Gilbert A.; Levy, Hal; Okie, William Bayard; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946; Toklas, Alice B., 1877-1967; Correspondence Press; Levy, Hal -- Ownership
- March 1962 Acquisition, 1936, undated; I_; 0.21; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 438.
  Custodial History
  Gift to Robert Bartlett Haas by Hal Levy.
  - "What are Masterpieces and Why Are There So Few of Them?" by Gertrude Stein, original typescript, with manuscript corrections by Alice B. Toklas; "An American in France," original typescript, with manuscript corrections by the author; autograph letter signed to the Conference Press from Gertrude Stein, 1936 September 17 with envelope addressed to Gilbert Harrison; leaf two of autograph letter signed to Robert Bartlett Haas, 1936, undated (Box 1)
    Accompanied by correspondence between Donald Gallup and Robert Bartlett Haas regarding the manuscript and letters, 1962 March
- December 1972 Acquisition, 1940-1941, undated; II_; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Levy, Harold. Various manuscript and typed notes and drafts for untitled article on Gertrude Stein, including a packet of 3x5 inch cards and two carbons of typescript article., undated (Box 2)
  - Conference Press material
    - Periodicals containing notices of What Are Masterpieces? and fourteen clippings about it and/or Gertrude Stein, mounted on cardboard, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
    - Unbound notebook containing addresses of libraries, universities, etc. and lists of names and address of individuals supplied by members of the publishing firm, undated (Box 2)
    - Sample stationary, forms, mailing labels, statements, envelopes, etc. Advertising folders for What Are Masterpieces?, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    - Envelope of material relating to sales and taxes, undated (Box 2)
- January 1986 Acquisition, 1985, undated; III_; 2
  Former call number: ZaSt34+G6 v.1 and ZaSt34+G6 v.5.
  - Souvenir program of "Gertrude Stein a Billignin. L'Universite de California, Los Angle en cooperation avec Madame G. Putz et ses enfant 25 Mai 1985 a 11 heures," two copies; two clippings (photocopies) on the "Gertrude Stein a Billignin" event; and 22 photographs (eight color and fourteen black and white photographs) of the "Gertrude Stein a Billignin" celebration and reception. (Box 3)
  - Reproduction of photograph of Gertrude Stein, undated (Box 3)
- 1989 Acquisitions, 1936-1985, undated; IV_; 0.84; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically by acquisition number.
  Contains correspondence, including letters from Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas to Robert Bartlett Haas; the contract for Stein's What Are Masterpieces?; writing draft of Stein's "Is Dead;" and papers relating to the production and distribution of Conference Press publications.
  - 23 autograph letters signed and 2 autograph postcards signed from Alice B. Toklas to Haas, with original envelopes, 1946-1955 (Box 3)
  - Clippings on What Are Masterpieces?, 1940 (Box 3)
  - 57 autograph letters signed and 12 autograph postcards from Gertrude Stein to Haas, 1936 October 26-1946 March 31; 4 (Box 4)
  - Original typed contract signed for Stein's What Are Masterpieces and autograph letter signed to Gilbert Harrison of the Conference Press, written on bottom of typed letter signed from Harrison to Stein, 1939 June 19, undated (Box 4)
  - Typed bound manuscript, corrected, of Gertrude Stein's "Is Dead", undated (Box 4)
  - Conference Press material
    - Title page designs for What Are Masterpieces? (Box 5)
    - Photograph of the directors of the Conference Press: Gilbert Harrison, Hal Levy and Jack Oakie (Box 5)
    - Correspondence to Haas from Conference Press, 1937-1940 (Box 5)
    - Three page manuscript by Hal Levy describing Gertrude Stein's manner of lecturing in California (Box 5)
    - Three letters from Edward Burns, William Baker, and Carl Van Vechten to Haas (Box 5)
    - Photograph of Stein's home in East Oakland (Box 5)
    - Seven pages from Sherry Terzian regarding Gertrude Stein exhibit, UCLA (Box 5)
    - Manuscript page of Virgil Thomson's scoring of an aria from "The Mother of Us All" (Box 5)
    - Letter from John Savage to Haas, with two xerox items regarding Alice B. Toklas's family in Seattle (Box 5)
    - Approval of proof for Haas's "A Primer for the Gradual Understanding of Gertrude Stein" with letter from Donald Gallup to John Martin (Box 5)
    - "Visages de L'Ain" with article in French by Stein (Box 5)
    - "Bugey Magazine" with an account of the 1988 3rd Stein Festival in Culoz/Belley and an account of the death of Rose d'Aiguy by Haas (Box 5)
    - 39 letters from Gertrude Stein Raffel to Haas (Box 5)
    - Seven programs about Stein conduced in California by Haas (Box 5)
    - Movie script for film based on Stein's "A Movie" by Sudy Dostal, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Six theater programs regarding Stein (Box 5)
    - Four announcements (Box 5)
    - Four postcards from Toklas to Haas (Box 5)
    - Three letters from Toklas to Haas (Box 5)
    - Issue of "Le Promeneur" (Box 5)
    - Letter from Gallup to John Martin (Box 5)
    - 35 items relating to Stein conference in Billignin, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Letter from Margery Tede regarding Stein Festival (Box 5)
    - Letter from Marta Feuchtwanger (Box 5)
    - Letter from Lady Rose (Box 5)
    - Letter from Donald Gallup (Box 5)
    - Letter from Maren Ellwood (Box 5)
    - Three letters from Marilyn Lingle regarding What Are Masterpiece (Box 5)
    - Letter from Samuel Steward (Box 5)
    - Letter from Arthur Uphill (Box 5)
    - Letter from Virgil Thomson to Haas (Box 5)
    - Two letters from Virginia Tufte regarding "Prothalamium" (Box 5)
    - Letter from Francoise Gilot Salk (Box 5)
    - Announcement of Haas lecture on Stein, 1967 (Box 5)
    - San Francisco Chronicle article on Alcoa exhibition, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Hal Holbrook review sent by Andy Hamilton to Haas (Box 5)
    - Ithaca College invitation to speak on Stein, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Review of Stein opera at UCLA, 1965 (Box 5)
    - University of Iowa Press to Haas, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence between Gilbert Harrison and Haas, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence between Mervin Lane and Haas, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Review book for "Gertrude morte cet apres-midi", Paris (Box 5)
    - Eight announcements of Stein books and programs (Box 5)
    - Signed edition of pamphlet "Is Dead" published by Haas and Krause (Box 5)
    - Typescript of Stein contract and response, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Letter from Alice B. Toklas, not in her hand (Box 5)
    - Carbon copy of letter from Haas to Toklas (Box 5)
    - Four newspaper articles (Box 5)
    - Letters from various individuals (Box 5)
    - Six letters and one postcard from Wilder Bentley regarding projected printing of Stein book in California (Box 5)
    - Twelve letters from Hal Levy of the Conference Press regarding the publication of What Are Masterpieces? (Box 5)
    - 21 additional items from Gertrude Stein Raffel concerning the Black Sparrow publication (Box 5)
    - Xerox of letters by Stein to Josette, a young girl in Culoz who had English lessons with her (Box 5)
    - Ten letters and three postcards from Thornton Wilder to Haas, including one long letter that outlines Wilder's conceptual thinking about Stein's work and how he was prepared to help Haas with his thesis on Stein, underway at the University of Chicago (Box 5)
    - Correspondence with various individuals (Box 5)
    - Material pertaining to the Black Sparrow Press and other topics (Box 5)
- May 1995 Acquisition, 1940, 962; V_; 0.21 linear feet (1 box)
  - What Are Masterpieces? galley proof, 1940 (Box 6)
  - "Gertrude Stein Talking: A Transatlantic Interview" by Robert Bartlett Haas, typescript carbon, 1962 (Box 6)